Finding Aid for L. May Helmer papers, 1907-1919
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
L. May Helmer papers 1907-1919
Helmer, L. May
0.4 linear feet
2014123 Aa 2
Nursing student at the University of Michigan who served as a nurse in France during World War I. Includes diary, correspondence, and photo album relating to her World I nursing service. Also certificates and a medal.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Received from the Helmer family in October 2013 (Donor no. 11002 ) through the Sindecuse Museum of Dentistry.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
Laura May Helmer was born December 13, 1881. She entered the Training School for Nurses at the University of Michigan in 1903 and graduated in 1906. She became head nurse of the Palmer Children's Ward and later moved to Bellevue Hospital. In 1917 she joined the Nursing Corps and served in France during World War I. Following the war she became a student in the University of Michigan dental hygiene program. She later moved to work at Berea Hospital in Kentucky.
The L. May Helmer papers primarily documents her service during World War I while she was stationed in Dijon, France. Material documenting her wartime nursing service includes a diary, correspondence, and a photo album/scrapbook. The photo album includes scenes aboard the SS Mongolia, scenes in the hospital including patients and staff, views of Dijon, France, travels in France, and a view behind German trench in Argonne Forest. Some family photos are also included in the album. Pasted into the album are various documents relating to transportation and her service with the Nursing Bureau. The papers also include a medal for service in World War I, a foreign service certificate, a 1911 certificate from the Michigan State Board of Registration of Nurses, and a 1907 photograph of the Alpha Theta Society.
Subjects:
Dental hygiene--Study and teaching--Michigan.; Dijon (France); Group portraits.; Helmer, L. May.; Hospital ships--British--1910-1920.; Nurses.; United States. Army Nurse Corps.; University of Michigan. Homeopathic Hospital. Training School for Nurses.; University of Michigan. School of Dentistry.; World War, 1914-1918--Women.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- L. May Helmer
  - Alpha Theta Society Photograph, 1907 (Box 1)
  - Certificates
    - Foreign Service Certificate, 1919 (Box 1)
    - Michigan State Board of Registration of Nurses, 1911 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1917-1918 (Box 1)
  - Diary, 1917 (Box 1)
  - Identification Card (Carte D'Identite), 1917 (Box 1)
  - Medals (Box 1)
  - Photo Album, 1917-1919 (Box 1)